welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
so check-ins uh
yeah i'm excited just sort of like a
calm excitement
so welcome to the stoa i'm peter limberg
the steward of the stoa
still is a place for us to cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
knife's edge
of this moment and today we
are lucky to have my buddy jonathan
peugeot
join us at the stoa jonathan
is a professional artist writer and
public speaker who gives workshops and
conferences
all around north america and he carves
eastern orthodox
icons and other traditional christian
images
and he has this excellent youtube uh
series called the symbolic world that
explores
symbols and images that are kind of
floating around in our our culture
uh so today jonathan is going to talk
about the ecstasy of 2020
and he's going to share his kind of
thoughts about what's happening all
the craziness that's happening in the
world and then we're going to have a
discussion
um so anytime jonathan's talking if you
have a question that comes alive
just write in the chat box and uh uh
when we get to the
q a portion i will call on you and uh
you can answer
ask your question to jonathan and uh if
you want me to read it on your behalf
because this will be on youtube
just indicate that in the chat and then
i will do so so that being
said i will unmute you jonathan and hand
it over to you
all right it's nice to meet everybody
i'm happy to be for the first time
on the stove i've been hearing a lot of
great things and uh you know i've been
following peter kind of from afar i
think i was on his podcast
a while ago and uh obviously read some
of his writing
as i'm sure most of you have very very
astute person so i'm happy to kind of be
in this little inner
clique that he's developed to uh to talk
about meaning and
problems with meaning and just the
madness of the situation
and so as everybody as everybody
probably saw
yesterday um well you two days ago
actually two days ago on the fourth of
july kanye west announced that he was
going to run for president of the united
states
and uh it's just very interesting
because
in january i think it was in january
early
2020 i when or
late 2019 i forget when kanye put out
his album
i actually started talking about kanye
west quite a bit i did three videos on
him
and it was actually the strange moment
where that there was a newsweek article
written about my take on kanye west for
some reason
and it just plays in everything nicely
plays into what is happening
and my contention for the past few years
is that we are in we're at the end of
something
you know you can see it how big as big
as you want to see it you know whether
it's the end of western civilization
whether it's the
end of one cycle of western civilization
the end of the enlightenment the end i
don't know when for sure
there's some there are many images which
are showing us that we're at the end of
something
and the the breakdown in meaning the
breakdown in unity
the and then also the the inversions
the fact that things keep flipping on
one side and the other
is a sign that we are you know can you
imagine like a wheel that's turning
and as it turns if you can imagine the
wheel gets bigger and bigger and bigger
or
you know the bigger it gets at some
point the wheel is going to start to
wobble
it is going to start to to lose its
coherence and that seems to be the point
where we're in
and in the ancient the ancients had a
vision of the world
and every culture had the same vision
that where they saw themselves as
let's say a center or an identity of
some kind and then as you moved out from
that identity
you had progressively stranger and
stranger people
obviously more people who were more
appeared stranger to you because they
were more different from you
and then as you moved out and out you
reached the monsters which were
you know these things that didn't you
how you didn't have name names for
the things that appeared to you as an
unknown
and then the further you went then you
reached the edge of the world where
you would see what appeared to you as
upside down behavior
the greeks of course had the uh
the amazons were the ultimate example
for the greeks because the greeks were
extremely
uh let's say male dominated and so they
had this image of something at the edge
of the world this tribe at the edge of
the world which was the opposite of them
and which was female dominated females
the the women were warriors and the men
were
barely around or barely important in
that society and so
that that that type of inversion can
play many roles like
it doesn't necessarily have to take on
one form it can take on many forms
but it it has its image in
the the vision of the world like this
kind of cosmic vision
but it also appears in our society as
well
in terms of a fringe element of our
society and i've used the carnival as
the ultimate example where
the carnival aesthetic seems to embody
mostly this fringe you know the the idea
of turning faster and faster
the notion of the freak show the note
all these images of the carnival
the clown the the acrobatics the whole
idea of turning and turning and turning
and so i the fact that things are so
unstable is
that's when we're starting to see these
these elements
come into play now the problem with the
the breakdown
is that there are also movements to try
to clamp down
and those two end up happening at the
same time and the danger that we
that we fall into is to want to take one
side or the other
we seem to think that we need to decide
which side we're on
either we're on the side of those who
want to break down the world
or on the side of those who want to
clamp things down and kind of
hold on for dear life you know and and
create
extreme versions of identity and extreme
versions of uh
of holding in and so we're gonna see
that it's gonna
it's gonna get worse i just wanna warn
you it's gonna get a lot worse
but we've started to see this kind of
playing out
and 2020 so when i made that video was
when i made that video about kanye west
in 2019 or early 2020 i told everybody i
said
hold hold on for 2020 because it's going
to be crazy
but i have to admit that i didn't expect
so much
to be happening in so little time but i
in
at the same time i'm not completely
surprised um
and so what we're seeing is
we're seeing this test of identity now
people don't realize
how a disease or how the pandemic was a
test of identity or was a
question of identity i think maybe
people can now
start to perceive it as they might have
perceived how
people's let's say even their alignment
in terms of what they would do for the
pandemic
ended up being more on political lines
rather than anything else
you know because the facts are so fluid
and they keep coming at it from all
these directions
people ended up taking taking political
lines for medical
in with medical uh medical veneer let's
say
but the reason why it's such a question
of identity
is because there's an analogy and it's a
scary analogy
but there is an analogy between the
person
and the the body politic there's an
analogy between a human being and a
society
and so just like
and you you can try to break that
analogy down but it
you it we're made to experience that
analogy
and what ended up happening with the
pandemic
was ended up being a question of walls
it ended up being a question of where
do you put the walls and that was is
we've been discussing that you know you
had donald trump saying build the wall
and then you had justin trudeau saying
diversity is our strength it's like
these two opposites like one is
build a wall the other is no identity
you know
just identity no identity this this
insane
type of rhetoric that we could see
coming up on on on both sides of the
political aisle
well the pandemic put that right into
your body
and it made it it linked the whole
meaning crisis into our bodies
and so the question became where do we
put the wall
how hard do we make the wall and
is the wall where is the value of the
wall
right and so because you could have said
well do we close down
borders for countries do we close down
borders
hierarchically in terms of we we see
where the breakouts are and then we shut
down walls
in different places or do we shut down
walls all the way down to the individual
and we separate everybody from each
other
and so that is if you want to understand
a lot of the debate that was happening
that was part of the large debate that
was going on
now the one that ended up winning seems
to have been the one where we separate
everybody from each other and we create
as
little as little uh fragmented bits
as possible and we shut down everything
now shutting down everything is is
interesting because the things we shut
down
are a lot of the things that people use
to
let's say to manifest their their
communal
aspect you know obviously we shut down
meetings we shut down churches we shut
down stores
we also shut down sports sports is a
huge deal
and it's bigger than a lot of people
think because the
there's a certain type of person which
really needs to identify
which really need to identify to have an
enemy and to have some kind of
fight and sports is actually a great way
to channel that
so that you actual that you avoid
conflict because you
give people the possibility of saying
this is my team i love my team
those that other team we're gonna beat
them you know and so it's a
it's a it's a less dangerous way of fun
obviously it can get out of control we
can see that in in england with the
hooligans and stuff
but it's the less dangerous way to
funnel identity and conflict
than let's say a social conflict but we
took that away we
took that away from everybody and so
everybody was just
in their home separated from each other
completely apart and then
something happened now it could have
been
other things but the thing that happened
made sense in terms of
the obviously the political narrative
that has been
that has been prevalent in universities
that have been prevalent
in uh in society in general
this idea of of a kind of neutral like a
kind of
a kind of rule of the margin you could
say and so we identified someone
we watched him get murdered and that's
really
when's the last time you watch someone
actually get murdered
we don't watch people get murdered we
watch it on tv we watch
movies but most of the time those images
are taken away from us
like most of the time we're not
permitted by media or whatever
and for some good reason to watch
someone be killed
but for some reason this this video
became
extremely available for everybody to
watch a man
be murdered during eight minutes
and then then there was a catharsis
explosion
because what happened in that murder
what happened in that murder is exactly
a catharsis it's exactly a classical
catharsis
because what we were asked to do
especially the white people like
especially the the
especially the westerners were asked to
identify with the victim
like obviously you want to identify with
the victim because
you you see this man suffer and you're
like this is unbearable
i can't stand watching someone be
tortured to death and it's driving you
crazy
but then you're also asked to identify
with the killer
and you're supposed to do that at the
same time you're supposed to both
identify with the person who's murdered
and identify with the killer and
the the i'll give you an example of
another place where that happens it's in
the story of
of christ that's another place where
that happens
where you're supposed to both identify
with christ
being killed but you're also supposed to
identify with those who killed christ
and so it was exactly a catharsis and
it led to a a
ex ecstatic explosion it led to an
ecstasy
and then people rushed into the streets
to protest to commune to commune
in the name of this cathartic moment
to commune in the shadow of this
catharsis
and all the images we saw the chanting
the kneeling
the the there were some crazier images
in that there were people being whipped
there were people washing the feet of
others there were
all these religious expressions of
of communion in the name of this
cathartic moment
and in the name of
of inclusivity you could say i don't
know how to name the value you could
call it inclusivity something like that
uh and there and then there was
scapegoating it's just inevitable there
was scapegoating
in the scent and it's weird scapegoating
because if you look at how the event
played through
uh like if you're trying to stay cool it
was hard to stay cool during that time
but if you looked at how the event
played out
you could see that everybody agreed that
this was horrible
everybody i don't think i ever i don't
think i saw anybody
who thought it was not horrible i mean i
saw i saw that
the man was arrested that the other
people
were put on i think they might have been
arrested too i don't even know but i
know they were for sure fired
and then everybody denounced it every
conservative every liberal
every politician at every level
denounced it
then every corporation denounced it i
received emails from every single
corporation that exists
you know denouncing what happened and
but for somehow
some reason there was still this idea
that we
all of these people everybody basically
who hated what to see this happen we're
the resistance
and we're the we're the we're the
resistance to the evil system
and we need to find those that are
responsible for the evil system
and because they're the system then we
can purge them
and we're totally justified in purging
them because we're the victims
and if we're the victims and the culprit
then even better reason
to now find those who are more
responsible than us and purge them from
the system
and so it was it was just a classical
scapegoating and it was a weird
scapegoating too because it was kind of
like
it was like it's always like this these
weird these like
shadowy figures that we never hear names
of it's like this evil system with like
evil white supremacists that are
managing it but it's like who are these
people i mean i guess donald trump is
one of the people
who who is kind of seen as the the one
to
to point to but in general it was like a
very much a kind of weird scapegoating
um and so it really did lead to a
pseudo-religious uh event
and i and and one of and the final
marker of the pseudo-religious event is
the human sacrifice
the human sacrifice is the the clincher
which makes it a religious event so
and you have to you have to see the
human sacrifice within
the narrative of the people who are
operating the sacrifice
so it's not even about being objective
or whatever or
the so cert a certain group of people or
as people on a certain side or people in
this certain side of the political aisle
said that you cannot go outside you're
not allowed to commune you're not
allowed to
get together with others you're not
allowed to to meet
if you do that you are killing your
grandmother
you are killing people if you come
together
and then they said you
should come together not because you're
not killing people
but because we are subjecting this to a
higher value
this is a higher value protesting racism
is
higher it is the ultimate value
under which we are ready to sacrifice
all other values underneath it
and we are also willing to sacrifice
people
and of course it wasn't conscious no one
said we're doing human sacrifice
but the pattern of human sacrifice was
exactly
being played out in their own narrative
um and so that is why everything looks
so weird
and so religious because it played it
followed a a very religious uh
pattern
now of course it's it's a frightening
it's a little frightening
in terms of pattern because it's not
clear how it's going to play out
it's not clear how the catharsis is
completely resolved
um i'm not sure how it's resolved in the
story
in the story of christ there is a
capacity for resolution right there's a
capacity for forgiveness
there's a capacity to come into
full communion with each other um
i'm i don't know if in this religious
moment there's
really a capacity for absolution
if there is i haven't seen it yet like i
haven't seen the capacity for absolution
and so it is a little frightening to uh
to watch this happen
and so it's going to continue uh it's
going to continue because
it this year's way it's far from being
over there's still an election
and now you have this fool character
kanye west who really does play the role
of a
of a fool uh who is now tossed in the
game
so what he so he is the real trump card
way more than donald trump
he is way more a trump card than trump
and so and
and it's funny because people are saying
he's there just to steal the votes from
biden
but i don't know he might be there to
steal the votes from trump
because he is he who knows because
people he's presenting himself as like a
conservative christian
who's married to kim kardashian i just
want you guys to realize how insane
the situation is uh and so he's he's
he's flying under the banner of a
conservative christian but obviously
you know i don't know you know he's
doing an album with dr dre
and he's and he's hanging out with kim
kardashe and he's married to kim
kardashian
and so who knows whose vote is gonna
take i don't know
but for sure like there's gonna be some
more madness
uh in this year coming along so i wish i
could offer
solutions to what we're seeing but right
now basically i can just
look and and watch with my jaw like just
fallen
and uh and hope for the best
cool um you ready for some yes sure
uh so we already have some questions in
the chat box uh just throw your
questions for jonathan i'm gonna warm
them up with a few
uh so if you if you recall when this
whole culvert thing came online
uh there was this meme that uh uh said
the virus broke woke
and it was sort of like it was quiet you
know the the woke stuff for a bit
uh and then just boom rushed online it's
like broke the virus
uh and it almost felt like the virus was
like a super ordinary goal that we could
kind of like instrumental
like you know rally behind together but
then didn't happen and i really liked
your frame with
the higher value thing um
[Music]
and it seems like you're you're sick
kind of like
what is it inclusion but it seems like
anti-racism is just
just one value and so is that
are we rallying behind right now or
what's the media and
it's not just anti-racism it's very
important to realize that black lives
matter
black lives matter very quickly put on a
very very large
black trans live matters black lives
matter the organization is not just
about black lives matter
it is about it is about the diversity
equity inclusion that's what it is and
that's why they
they made they hurried up to put out a
a black trans live matter because they
wanted to signal
that it is about inclusion and it is not
just about
not just about uh racism there's that
there's a
there's a bigger aspect to this thing
that is not just
it's not only captured by racism mm-hmm
yes so what i was going to say is that
is it a positive value like conclusion
or is it like a negative value like you
know
not this like anti-racism or something
and you think it's more of a
inclusion positive value that's that's
being gestured in this ecstasy
well it's inclusion
inclusion is not a positive value
necessarily
it can be positive and it can be
negative it's like
every it's like everything everything in
excess is is dangerous and so
absolute inclusion now one of the one of
the things that i've been
trying to explain or how people
understand is
the role of the margin and what
marginality is
and it's let's say the power of the
margin
the function of the margin and the
dangers of the margin
now one of the dangers with the
inclusivity
proposition that is being presented is
that
we want to include everything
equally in an equal measure
and so what we want is we want the
exception
to be equal to the rule
and that doesn't work that type of
inclusion
will break the system it'll break
everything
because in order to crea in order to
take something marginal and try to make
it equal to the rule
the only way to do it is to
flip to make it upside down is to
emphasize the margin
is to make the margin the rule it's the
only way to do it
because it naturally it just it just
doesn't it's
there are things in the world which are
just naturally marginal that are just
that are just freaky that are just
things that
happen once in a while that are that are
and and they have a power which is
useful in the world like they're they're
useful for society
that we have these that we have the
freak shows that we have the the
things that are that are strange on the
on the edges but if you try to make so
here okay so
let me phrase it in a way let me phrase
it in a way that is
that is easy to understand but is scary
in its implications
and so you have a a country
right and this country has a limit
right and then on the outside of that
country then you have everything that is
strange all the strangers all the
foreigners now they're
innumerable and they have they have
multiple identities
they have an indefinite amount of
identities because the outside is always
bigger than the inside
and so what happens when you want to
make the stranger
more important than that which is inside
or if you want the stranger to be
equally included on the inside as the
inside
then you it things get loopy very fast
because you end up having you end up ha
because the the one who's inside has a
natural
has a natural advantage on the inside
because they're on the inside they're
part of the group they're part of the
identity it doesn't matter which
which type it could be a knitting club
or it could be a soccer club or it could
be a country
or a sadly it can also be things like a
race or
things like a religion it can be all
kinds of things now
if you want now to include everything
you have to do it in a way to you have
to
prioritize that which is outside because
that which is outside
inside naturally has advantage so you
end up prioritizing that which is
outside
and then things get crazy loopy things
start because then what is this thing
it's all gonna fall apart it's it's
inevitably gonna fall apart
i always kind of joke like if you have a
knitting group
and then and then there's like you know
i don't know like betty has a friend in
her knitting group who comes to the
knitting group but she doesn't really
knit right she's just there
to hang out or maybe to talk to others
because she likes people and that's
totally fine
uh but then what if you you want her to
be equal to all the other members of the
knitting group
it's going to get really complicated
because then she says well i don't want
to knit
i want to do something else like i want
to play play
bowling or something so it's like okay
well once in a while we'll have a
bowling event because
we want to include you in the group but
then
at some point it's going to start to
break down you know
anyways that that's that's the problem
of the of the oh
that can be that's the danger of equal
inclusion it just it just
can't just can't work in terms of a
system
so we're going to pivot to some
questions a lot of good questions
popping up
uh but ask one more uh does kanye have a
chance
to win yeah i can't i can't say
my goodness there anything's possible
right now
anything is possible i don't know what i
i
i to be honest for all my love of kanye
west like i've followed kanye west since
since his first album 2004 i think and i
love his music
and i think he's a fascinating person
but i i hope he doesn't win
but anything's possible at this point
kim kardashian first lady
the store is going to wait to see uh who
it endorses for 2020 so this whole tight
it might be easy so rain you had a
question as related to kanye actually
maybe we can
double click on that one yeah well i'd
be curious
maybe others are more aware than i am i
don't spend a lot of time on social
media i haven't followed kanye
i just hear indirectly about him i also
didn't watch your videos so
if there is other interest in the group
i was just curious if you wanted to
summarize any of your analysis and
just say anything else about what role
kanye is playing and
everything that's happening so so my so
my contention in general about the fool
is that the fool is the one who's
who turns things you know so the image
of the clown is perfect he's on a ball
he's rolling a ball he's juggling
uh and so the fool is the one who turns
things and so when
when things are going well what the full
tia tends to do is to turn things upside
down
right to show the upside down of
something so the king is all pompous and
is
is is extremely proud of himself and so
the king will lift up
the his skirt and will point to the
thing that's hidden right he'll point to
the
to the to the hidden things which are in
the shadows let's say
and so the clown is always kind of
turning things right and he's
emphasizing excess
caricature all of that now
the the problem is that when the world
is upside down
then what's the role of the clown when
everything is already topsy-turvy
what does the clown do well the clown
keeps turning
the clown will turn things and so what
i've been trying to point out is that
when the world is is upside down watch
the fools because the fools
are the ones who are actually going to
turn things right side up
um who are going to turn things back
towards order
and so i saw that already in kanye
a long time ago in 2004 he did this song
called jesus walks
which was a really strange song because
it's a song about
about street life and hustling and all
these things
but then he's he he talks about how
jesus walks with the lowest basically so
he's saying
you know he's talking about he needs to
go do a drug deal and he's going to
leave his mom to do a drug deal
and he says i hope that jesus walks with
me and so he's connecting like the
highest thing with the lowest okay
um so i was really i've been watching
him since then
and now he he basically became
like a conservative christian
he he had a conversion experience and uh
he's now he's all like pro family pro
ev he's he's all about uh he's ex
he's become super conservative um and
he's not the first one for who that
happens
i've been watching certain characters in
in
in the past few years one of the
examples i give is gavin mcginnis who
obviously he's been really really kind
of thrown around in the media but
as a character he was interesting
because he founded vice news
and he was he was a he was a punk he was
a punk
pervert all this stuff and all this
at some point it's like the whole world
became like him what does a punk do when
the whole world is punk rock
and so he he actually he's like i can't
stand this and then he started to point
back to
the to the to normalcy got married
had kids became a knights of columbus uh
you know started wearing buttoned up
shirts and it's like he was just it's
like
the when when the the world is
exceptional the exceptional
points back to the rule it happens very
naturally and so kanye i think that
that's what kanye is doing so if you
look at his tweet it's crazy because he
says
we need i forget the exact wording but
it's like we need to follow god and to
find
our unifying principle or whatever and
that's why i'm running for
president of the united states that's
kanye west
who is writing that like you know the
guy
the guy who would dress up in a big
teddy bear suit that guy
that guy is saying we need to go back to
god and find our unifying principle
and so that's what i mean when i talk
about the fool kind of
watching the fool at the end because the
fool is the one who's going to bring
back
to bring back order for i mean whether
you agree with the order he brings back
or not
that's not even the point to watch it as
a phenomena is to to just see it happen
like
kanye west is more conservative than
donald trump
that's how weird this world is
all right does that help i understand a
little bit what i was talking about
do you have any follow-up questions
right
no thank you okay uh
jacob you had a question
it's my mic working yeah
hi jonathan um
so my question is to do with what
what is the relationship between the the
current
um movement and the christian substrate
in the kind of unconscious layer
and just one more piece i want to attack
on to this is
if we're kind of stepping back to like
the mid 19th century around like
nietzsche
um and if this movement has kind of
marxist foundations
and what's the relationship between the
and christianity as well with marxism
kind of coming out of the same substrate
so any anything that would be great
what i would i've tried to point to
is that the modern world is basically
the breakdown of christianity and so
i mean it's there historically that's
what it is you know it's the the
the rise of scientific atheism the the
rise of
of uh just a basic cultural atheism you
could say
or secularism and so what happens in
that
what happens in that breakdown of
christianity
is that christianity starts to pull
apart and so certain aspects of
christianity start to manifest
disorder in a disordered manner and so
there is an aspect of christianity
which is an attention to the little one
right attention to the poor um
and a desire for
a form of
i would say it that way i would say
attention to the poor attention to the
margin
right christ goes out finds the lost
sheep
yeah the the there's all these images in
christianity obviously just the
beatitudes are
a lot about that and so that
value in itself is good but it's it's
dangerous if it's just taking taken on
its own
it's very dangerous um and that's what i
think
one of the aspects of marxism is it's
that it's
it's a it's it's a desire for when we
know it it's like it's a it's a utopian
desire it's a desire for
a certain aspect of utopia and
their their vision of utopia is a kind
of equality
utopia and then there are other utopias
and we saw them in the 20th century
which are hierarchical utopias
and so those two are gonna now those two
are what led to world war
ii a hierarchical utopia and an
an and an egalitarian utopia
and we're going to see it happen again
because we never dealt with it
and it's the same movements it's just
hilarious it's it's not funny but it's
hilarious
because you you want to you go you go
online and look for antifa images from
the 1920s in germany
you'll be surprised that that's one of
the one of the things that led to the
to to where germany ended up was
the very same questions that we're
dealing with now
and people are really struggling because
there's a desire for a secular utopia
and so the idea in the religious context
is that
if the highest thing is the highest
thing so i say it's like i say the
highest thing
is the infinite or the highest thing is
being
or the highest thing is love right being
love
infinite then
it's not a value in terms of morality
right it's something beyond the value in
terms of morality
morality will flow out of it um
but but it's not an absolute it's not a
it's not a value
and so what we're seeing now is exactly
that it's and so
there is definitely the blm is
definitely marxist like the the founders
are marxist
their desires are extremely marxist in
their formulations
and they're using i don't know how
conscious it is but they're definitely
used
using kind of religious imagery to get
people
on board and to get people excited about
about their project and so i don't
but there is no there is no happy ending
to this to that story
like that there is no happy ending to
what to what blm
is asking for it can't end well
so relatedly amy you had a question
yeah hi jonathan sorry it's a
thunderstorm here i hope uh
it's easy to hear me yeah i had a
question
about the kind of uh what i've been
noticing about this kind of uh
there's a relationship i see between
text and image and the pseudo-religious
moment
um and i was wondering if you thought
that it connected to the past
and that there seems to be a dual uh
call to
for iconoclasm to destroy images in the
form of statues
and also to worship certain new texts
that's the right fragility is
like the best-selling book in the united
states right now so i wonder if we had
any thoughts about that
yeah well one of the when i talk about
the end of something
one of the images of the end is
iconoclasm
that is when something breaks down you
you want to break down the memory of it
because you the image i often give is
if you if you buy a house and you when
you move into the house
you find that people have left pictures
of their family there
the first thing you're going to do is
you're going to remove the pictures of
the people's family so that you can
settle
in now that has normal implications but
it also has very dark implications if
you play it out in terms of social
social questions now
one of the things that's happening now
it's not that we're it's not like a
switch of house but it's actually
people who are trying to break down the
identity of the family break down the
identity of those
that have held the house until now and
so when you see iconoclasm
it's it's definitely a it's a transition
it's it's a transition towards other
statues
it's a transition for you to put then
other ideals up there for people to to
venerate
so and some of the stuff that they're
pulling down maybe should be pulled down
it's possible
like there's some you know there's a
there's some dark stuff in the u.s south
maybe i don't know
you know it's not i'm not it's not it's
not my thing i
i'm canadian i'm french canadian i have
other markers
you know there are people there are like
there are people here there's
curry label here in canada and there are
statues of him
and there are some dark aspects to his
story but to be honest i don't think it
would be a good idea to pull down
his statue because he did found you know
large swaths of the north here
but there are dark aspects and so one of
the
the way that i framed it too is the the
idea of of hiding
the nakedness of your father and so
in the world of all identities
are no identity is perfect all
identities
are broken because they're not they're
not let's say they're not
god right and so all identities have a
brokenness to them
and so in order in order for them to
hold together one of the things you have
to do is you have to hide their
nakedness
and i take that from the story in the
bible where noah
the father the new father right so
there's a flood everything's destroyed
now there's noah he's going to be the
father of everybody else right the whole
world is going to be
is going to be related to noah and then
he gets drunk and he passes out naked in
his tent
and one of his sons sees him naked and
makes fun of him
because he's naked and then he's cursed
because of that
now his other sons go in and they hide
his nakedness they cover his nakedness
okay
so you have to understand it as in order
to preserve an identity you have to to a
certain extent
hide the nakedness of your father
the the problem is always knowing when
is it too much
like when are you hiding too much but
everybody does it
right imagine you have a basketball team
and your star player has some
negative aspects to them well you don't
want to be publicly telling everybody
about
the bad habits of your star basketball
player because you won't you don't want
your basketball team
to be dismantled and you don't want to
lose and it's the same for
any team any church any school any group
and so we need to hide the nakedness of
our father
but at some point and so at some point
you have to stop if it's too much right
because we saw too much of it like all
the
priests abusing children and then people
covering up for them
all the coaches abusing children all
that kind of stuff is when you do it too
much
now the problem is that if you hide the
nakedness of your father
it's still there the scandal is hidden
but it's still there
and at some point at in the end
it's going to appear it's going to show
itself
the system is going to play itself out
the weakness of the system that you hid
at the beginning is going to be its
downfall
at the end and it's going to be what the
your enemies use to destroy
and it's just inevitable it's just going
to happen that way and so
america has sins in its origin
it has hidden sins and the hidden sin is
that that which they declared which is
equality fraternity uh freedom
in their founding they hid a sin which
is that it wasn't
true for everything that they in
in in saying that they also hid their
own
sins and now they're coming out and they
they have been coming out
but it's it's hard it's hard to avoid
that happening at some point now i don't
know when
it's supposed to happen but it's hard
for that to not to not happen
but it and we have to be careful not to
point fingers because
this what i'm telling you is true of
every system
and it's true of every family and it's
true of every
any organization has hidden since
um it's just part of a system
okay so we have a lot of questions we're
not gonna get to all of them
but we've got dominic you got a question
sure thanks hi jonathan hey can you
point us the stories
in anticipation of the inclusion or
exclusion
of those who don't choose the side of
either the breakdown or the clampdown
if i can find those that don't choose
either or
it usually ends up in the stores usually
don't look they don't look very pretty
they don't end up in a
so okay i'll give you i'll give an
example where both sides are shown
next to each other okay um so
it's in the story of exodus in the story
of exodus
the israelites leave egypt
and when they leave egypt they gather
all the rabble with them
so it's basically you can imagine that
as these slay as these israelite slaves
are being freed and are leaving israel a
bunch of people were like well i'm
getting in on this
and so they like gathered a whole bunch
of mixed
people and who who knows like who they
were but just a bunch of people
and so they come into the desert and
then
the the israelites complained that they
don't have what they need they complain
they complain
and then at some point they complain too
much it doesn't matter for what
the idea is that they complain too much
and it says in scripture that it's the
mixed multitude
that complained too much and you can
understand
why that would happen because if you're
if you don't feel like this is yours
like if you don't feel you're part of a
group
then you have it's easier to complain
because you're not covered by the
advantages of the group as much
you have less cover from the advantages
so it's easier for you to complain and
it's more
it's normal that you'll be the one who
complains the longest who are complains
the most
right um and then in scripture what
happens
is god ends up giving them what they
complain about
but he purges the edge of the camp
and so there's a purr like a fire that
burns the edge of the camp
okay that's some scary stuff man i told
you it's scary stuff
now right after that story like the
chapter right after that short
story there's a there's a balance to it
which is that moses is married to an
ethiopian
which like in let's say in ancient
thinking the ethiopian was like
the ultimate foreigner right we don't
even know exactly who what actual people
they were referring to
but it was like referring to those
people really that live like on the edge
of the world like they're so far we
don't know exactly like they're very far
and so he was married to an ethiopian
woman
and the the idea is that she was dark
like she was dark skinned you can see it
in the story that she was dark skinned
because
moses's sister complains about the fact
that he's married to a foreigner and
married to an ethiopian
and then because of that she gets a
disease which is that she becomes
too white her skin becomes white like
snow
and because she becomes white like snow
she has to be excluded
from the group and she has to be cast
out of the
of the camp because of that so you can
see the two problems like
you could call it an excess of mixture
and an excess of purity
and those two things happening you know
one after the other
and almost being like uh like a call
upon each other because you can imagine
that after the mixed multitude problem
the reason why miriam was complaining
was because well we just had this mixed
multitude problem now moses is married
to a a stranger
so it's like it one led to the other and
i would say that in terms of what's
going on right now we need to be
attentive to that
especially because things don't ever go
just in one direction
they're gonna go in one direction and
then they're gonna snap back
like when nazi when hitler was elected
in germany they were on the verge of a
communist revolution
it didn't just happen like it didn't
just happen
when everything was fine it's like you
pull the
the pendulum here it gets pulled in the
other way and it's hard to know which
way is going to win
like it could have been the other way
maybe the com maybe hitler could have
failed in his coup and then the
communists could have taken over and
and and germany could have ended up you
know sending people to the gulag like
who knows
but that's the problem is that one calls
the other
so i hope that story is at least one
example of those two extremes
kind of appearing in the story
maybe gray you had a question that'd be
good to
piggyback on this one yeah
hi jonathan thanks so much for being
here um
my question was about um i i i don't
know what your perception is but
my perception is that most people in
secular society don't really understand
secular society to be like broken up
cluttered down
christian commitments um and i was just
wondering if you think that
that sort of ignorance is like
exacerbating
the sort of dangers that these
pseudo-religious events
pose for us all yeah i totally think so
i think that that our our
the fact that we despise history and uh
we don't know about history is really
a call for all of this to to keep
getting worse because
we don't understand what's happening
everybody is is moving from one side to
the other
and nobody nobody knows what's going on
and so it's not so it ends up having a
being a caricature of liturgical events
a caricature of the surgical feast the
caricature of
of like the ancient celebrations that
people used to have but
no one knows what's happening and so the
idea the idea is that these patterns
like
this is why like for example like i'll
call out someone like stephen pinker
which is that people are saying people
are saying oh look at these
these you can see it people some of the
kind of atheist types they look at these
events and they're like oh here again is
a horrible
manifestation of of our religious
tendency you know and so they they decry
it they're like oh this is horrible that
we shouldn't
this is just another example of this
kind of horrible stuff but the problem
is
that it's not going to go away because
you say that
you know those patterns are in you those
patterns are part of you
they're like the example i always use is
you can complain that people sleep
because they're not productive
but they're still going to sleep you can
say if you didn't sleep you would be
more productive but it doesn't matter
it's still gonna happen
the question is how does it happen does
it happen haphazardly and chaotically
and we end up
scapegoating and sacrificing people and
and like
beating people in the street or do we
have a
ordered version which is what religion
offers
which is what you know this is which is
what christianity offered but other
religions offer that as well
uh give a a place to funnel all those
desires into
a kind of dance where instead of
actually killing each other
we're dancing together
thanks so much okay
uh aaron rodgerson you had a question
i feel like that question was just kind
of answered but uh
you hi jonathan you mentioned um sports
have sort of a
healthy way of channeling tribalism
in a way and i was saying does religion
in some sense have the same effect
and did religion evolve to
combat chaos and are we returning to a
pre-religious
time of collapse and chaos in some ways
well i think religion what religion does
is more complicated than that
it's not about combating chaos it's
about integrating
it all together and so
one of the things that i that i talk
about it's like
christianity for example like
christianity is a religion where we look
at someone who is nailed to a cross
what the hell i mean it's not a just
about
bringing order it's about integrating
the whole thing
right it's about integrating the entire
thing death to
all the bad stuff too how do we
integrate the whole thing
how do we bring it all together and and
you know as much the order and the light
as the death and the darkness we have to
be able to kind of
bring it all together or else it's going
to appear in
in kind of other ways now this is why
this is why
the people who try to combat the chaos
you know
let's say the enlightenment that's why
they have a shadow that's why they have
uh
as as pika pinker says that counter
enlightenment
it's just so hilarious as if you can
avoid it like as if
you could have just the enlightenment
and not have the counter enlightenment
that's just not how it works that's not
how systems work and so
the counter enlightenment is just gets
stronger until it explodes
and then we have insanity and we have
crazy manifestation
so so yeah so i think it i think
religion
offers more than just order it offers an
integration it can be tribalistic too
like no doubt i don't want to pretend
that it's not
and it can have tribal it can become
tribal and it can have extremely
it can be dangerous of course it can but
it's all about
choosing choosing which one is the most
is the least uh is the least going to
destroy everything
thank you all right um
so i'm going to read this on stephen's
behalf how could the absolution play out
in a culture that seems to believe that
no one is redeemable
uh cancel culture what are the
alternatives
ah i don't think i don't think that it
can work i don't think it's gonna work
i'm really look i hate to say this
but the only way for it to work is
scapegoating
that's it that's the way for it to work
and uh and it seems like we're already
we're seeing a lot of that
um but it can escalate seriously
escalated to the two minutes of hate
i mean that's that's the only way out of
it
because the the only way for the
like the white liberal to get out of
their
of their let's say guilt
is to find someone who's more guilty
than them and then turn around and
scream at them
right there's no other way and so that
that will you know that will
like pile up if you
watch the the cultural revolution stuff
like the maoist stuff you want to see
where this goes it's insane
you'll have your people be dragged
dragged out into public
and publicly humiliated publicly
i mean i don't know how far it can go in
in north america but
it's it's it's scary stuff
and what's the alternative like the
alternative is is confession the
alternative is sacramentality
the alternative is real community uh
you know that's that's the the the
that's the alternative
like one of the roles that let's say
like for example i'm orthodox like
that's one of the roles a confession
plays
a confession is a way to to acquire
absolution uh but it involves
accepting a form of hierarchy um
so uh i do have we're almost at the top
of the hour can i sneak in
one more question yeah i'm totally fine
i'm i'm having fun so it's it's fine
cool cool cool so yeah on the orthodox
piece uh let's see if i can like
jam in two questions here so one
question is what do you think of our
buddies john's uh
religion without a religion a religion
that's not a religion however he phrases
it
and then the other one um because i'm
baptized as orthodox christian uh and
then you were talking about
um you know there's this reversal with
guys like gavin mcginnis or doing the
360 and kind of like rouge
we were talking about the pickup artist
that was a wild one he joined our
our religion and then um and there's
just i don't really know this phenomenon
the ortho bros
you you've heard these like these yeah
and that's just rising up
um so yeah and so what's the the genre
i'm curious your thoughts on that and
what is your thoughts in the orthodox
christianity and the role that it could
play
in this this sort of like ecstasy yeah
the ecstasy man well i i think i don't
obviously i don't agree i don't agree
with the
with the religion that's not a religion
i i think
that
i think that there are certain aspects
of humanity which are inevitable
and if you don't take them into account
because you don't like them
they're just going to come back it
doesn't matter
you can't avoid it you can try but
they're going to come back and so
and so i understand john's fear
like his fear of narrative for example
like i understand his fear of narrative
because because it can be exclusionary
you know because it's idea
because it does create identity and it
creates exclusion so i understand it's
fear
but there's no way around it
there's no way around it it's going to
come back and so
so for example so like john john talks
about
how he doesn't want narrative but he
does have a narrative
right he spent 30 hours in his podcast
giving us
the narrative of his religion without a
religion which is
the narrative of the the
breakdown of christianity and the the
the rise of the enlightenment and now
reaching the end and now like in a
post-enlightenment world so there is
there is a a narrative
and
there's something of the tower of babel
in what he's trying to do which is
the desire to create a tower that
includes everything
that doesn't have that doesn't have an
outside
and it just it's just not possible
now the idea is to find a way
to is to find a way to have an
outside or to have a margin which has a
role
and which you can encounter and that you
can engage with
rather than just try to not have one or
not have a narrative
or just be the margin or just be it's
like you need to have the whole
you need to have the whole thing so i
don't think i don't think uh
i don't think that it can work um
uh i mean can it work individually like
to help people out
yeah i think so i think so i mean i'm
sure
john has helped a lot of people and i've
seen a lot of people really
feel like he's helped them through the
meeting crisis and everything and so so
like i i take
anything that helps people get out of it
is great i think it's wonderful
so i agree but i i think that
i think that as a let's say as a
movement or as a kind of social thing
let's say this way let's say it in
evolutionary terms uh
if you have something which is too
general
something which is specific is going to
come like a needle it's going to burst
your thing
and that's it and that's the same so so
if you don't want to have a narrative
and you you create this this kind of
amorphous like
uh emergent thing without a narrative
then those that have a narrative are
going to come in and they're going to
slash you to pieces
and they're going to take over your
territory and it's just going to happen
um yeah so as for orthodoxy look at what
role can orthodoxy play
uh i think like for me i can just talk
for myself look guys like i just talked
for myself like
i feel like i felt like i feel like
western christianity lost the plot at
some point
that they lost the higher aspects the
mystical aspects
they lost the the the the kind of
system of traditional of sacred language
they lost they kind of lost it and so
as our own system breaks down so
i talk about this idea of the of the
foreign or the mixed
the mixed multitude or the thing on the
margin so you actually need that stuff
you need a little bit of it especially
when
the system is exhausted you actually
have to go outside
and get some fuel from the outside and
so my
sense is that orthodoxy is sufficiently
strange but not too strange
in order to to revivify some aspect of
the west
you know and so i think that it has a
lot to offer and it has a lot
a lot to offer people who who want to be
catholic or what even want to remain
protestant or whatever
i think that it can have a lot to offer
because it it has enough strangeness
that it doesn't feel
like the evil system that you want to
fight and it ha
it has like that uh it has the the uh
the appeal of the orient you know that
kind of
that kind of cliche of like the golden
turbine wearing uh
you know like that that imagery that you
saw you know pop up in the romanticism
of like the
the east full of treasures it has enough
of that
um but it also has enough connection
that it's not completely
odd like it's not completely off you're
not just being an idiosyncrasy
in society you know that's one of the
things that i
struggle with kind of the i call the
california buddhist
is that it's so idiosyncratic
to be a buddhist in in in america that
i mean you can do it it's good it might
help you but it's
it's your b you're still fragmenting the
thing you're still participating in the
fragmentation by doing that
so that's what i think that's one of the
things i think orthodoxy can offer
i don't that makes sense
and it's a very very uh beautiful
religion if you look into it just
experience it go to church
check it out um do you think it's on the
rise too because i i noticed
uh more people are talking about it and
on the website well
it seems like it's hard because it's
hard because we're all in our bubble but
for sure in my perception i've had a lot
of people
interested and you know uh interested in
the mysticism christian just interested
in christian mysticism
reading the church fathers i think that
like i think that some of the key saints
some of the key think
thoughts in orthodoxy offers really good
solutions to the problems like i
i really think say maximus the confessor
offers
one of the best solutions to the problem
of of emergence
of the of the relationship between
consciousness
and phenomena or the relationship
between
meaning and you know what kind of john
vervicky talks about
the problems of relevance realization i
think that uh
sa maximus offers the the most
integrated solution
of both bottom up and top-down uh
approach at the same time so
from the top you have name identity
which kind of comes down
and acts as an authority but from the
bottom you also have the notion of the
coming together
of the elements so it's like the joining
the fitting together
in love happening at the bottom and then
also the naming the head this image of
the top so
it's not just top down but it's also not
just a kind of
puzzling emergence where it's like okay
you use that word but i don't know what
you're
like how does it come together you need
those two to happen at the same time
um so we passed the hour do you want to
sneak in one more question or should we
end here it's up to you guys i'm
i'm cool if you still have attention
yeah so there's a a good question so
we'll ask this one um uh he wanted to
read it
on his behalf as well jordan peterson uh
and i'm curious to get your download on
your thoughts on how jordan's doing if
you watched his recent video with his
daughter
um so with points by jordan peterson and
yourself do you believe that the role of
symbols and myths could be recognized
and integrated in science as we know it
today
does science have room or does the
boundaries of science have to be broken
to accommodate symbols and myths
so okay
the way that that myth and and religious
imagery is going to be
integrated into science is through
the science of of the human being it's
through looking back at the human being
and not not ignoring
the experience of consciousness right
and
as we look back on consciousness as we
try to use consciousness to look back on
it
then all of a sudden i think that that's
the way
that these that science can
see the
it won't be scientific right but it can
see the the reason for these stories and
these patterns and the
and these myths and also understand that
science itself is always submitted to
purpose
there's always a reason why you do
things and
once you when you ask what that reason
is
that's when you start to see these
stories come back in
and so it's not in the d it's not in the
analysis it's not in the thing but it's
the reason why you analyze
which is subject to to mythological
storytelling
right so let give you an example right
so we developed the atom bomb but
we just developed an atom bomb we didn't
just develop an atom bomb
we were in a war and we had these
enemies and there was a race
who was going to get the atom bomb first
and so finally the americans
took some of the enemy scientists
brought them to themselves
and then created this atom bomb so that
they could defeat
the last remnants of the war and win the
war
without that story there's no atom bomb
there is none why would you make an atom
bomb
you'd have to be pretty insane to make
an atom bomb to be honest
you need that narrative in order to to
to justify the research
and so that it so i gave you an extreme
example
but it's like that for everything we
always have a reason to study things
yeah yeah that's really really well put
um so i think we'll
end it here uh do you have any closing
thoughts for us at the
stowa well thanks i i
i'm just happy to see people try to
figure things out
and to to ask the hard questions and to
also be willing to talk about things
without just letting ourselves be
polarized try to see both sides
try to understand at least the reason
why the two sides
appear let's say in debates and so um
so i appreciate it and i wish you all
the best did you have any thoughts on
stoicism actually because you know a lot
of people say they're like
proto-christians
i'm not sure if you have any thoughts i
do have a thought on socialism
my thought on sources is that stoicism
only works if it's integrated into
christianity
uh for the same reason as what i'm
talking about in terms of the religion
without a religion
i think stoicism offers great
practice great advice great moral
uh teaching but because it never offered
a narrative
that i think that it just it couldn't
win and that's why i didn't win
and i think that once stoicism became
integrated within
the christian story then that's when it
actually took on
its best fruits that's when and that's
why when people look at
early christian saints and they say well
that's just a stoic i'm like yeah
i don't mind that i don't have a problem
with that
because but it's a he's a stoic because
this is integrated
into also a cosmic story and
a social story and a and a communion
a reason to commune and that's what
makes
that's what made the stoic that's what
made stoicism flower
in the christian age um so that's what i
think of sources
right right cool um so thank you so much
my friend for visiting the stoa we hope
to have you back
um so i'll make a few announcements on
upcoming events
uh we have like tons so just go to the
website the store.ca but
um there's two uh tonight that i will
mention
uh one is steal the culture with john
verveiki in the cure the dawn that is at
seven
p.m eastern time so john like when his
first appearance of the stoa he
mentioned something like
we gotta steal the culture from the
people who have been abusing us for so
long
and then it was like such a cool line uh
i sent it to akira and then he made like
a
a dance song out of it and so we're
going to preview that at the stoa
and john and akira are going to have a
talk and then we're going to have a talk
together
against some deal logos which should be
fun um
and then our boy tyson has an event
tonight uh in our wisdom gym
i think tyson is here so if you can
unmute yourself uh
tyson you can kind of plug that sure
thanks peter
thank you jonathan yeah the event is
flowing with unknowingness that is at 8
30 eastern time
it's a very playful and musical
experience where we practice deepening
our relationship with
uncertainty through freestyle rap
and spoken word and i'd love to see
as many of you as possible there it's a
lot of fun for me
and i'm sure jonathan is going to join
us on the freestyle tonight and give us
a
show some bars hot bars
um okay so the the still is based off a
gift economy we view it as a gift
uh for all of us to use this time of
need if you're inspired to provide a
gift to the store you can go to the
store dot ca
slash gift um yeah so thank you so much
everyone
thank you thanks again jonathan
okay boom